A Guide to the Rockefeller Foundation records, officers' diaries, RG 12, F-L FA392
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Fahs, Charles B.
  - Trip to Canada, Japan, and Okinawa - Index, 1959 April 4-May 2; Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Humanities.; Fahs, Charles B. (Charles Burton) (Reel M Fah 7, Frame 5, Box 145)
    indexes (reference sources); Humanities; Japan; Education; Canada
  - Trip to Canada, Japan, and Okinawa, 1959 April 4-May 2; Fahs, Charles B. (Charles Burton); Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Humanities.; 69 pages (Reel M Fah 7, Frame 7, Box 145)
    Fahs tours various Universities in Japan and Canada.
    Canada; Diaries; Education; Japan; Humanities
  - 1959 May 4-October 9, Fahs, Charles B. (Charles Burton); Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Humanities.; 170 pages (Reel M Fah 7, Frame 77, Box 145)
    Fahs visits the American Symphony Orchestra League and the Twelfth American Dance Festival. He attends the Conference on English Language Teaching in Egypt and the Soviet-Asian Relations Conference. He also surveys an electronic music project at Columbia University.
    Music; United States; Language and languages; Linguistics; Encyclopedias and dictionaries; Diaries; Humanities; Dance; Art; Education
  - Trip to England - Index, 1959 October 11-21; Fahs, Charles B. (Charles Burton); Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Humanities. (Reel M Fah 7, Frame 247, Box 145)
    Index; Trip to England; 3 pages.
    Education; England; Humanities; indexes (reference sources)
  - Trip to England, 1959 October 11-21; Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Humanities.; Fahs, Charles B. (Charles Burton); 57 pages (Reel M Fah 7, Frame 250, Box 145)
    Fahs travels to England and tours Oxford, Cambridge and London for RF Humanities grant programs.
    Linguistics; Humanities; Language and languages; England; History; Diaries; Education
  - 1959 October 22-December 31, Fahs, Charles B. (Charles Burton); Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Humanities.; 95 pages (Box 145, Reel M Fah 7, Frame 307)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Fahs discusses projects and proposals with professionals in the field of humanities. He is involved in the progress of Humanities Division programs, selection of fellows and grant in-aid, and development of new research. The aims of the Humanities Division are to identify and stimulate new cultural growth, assist in interpretative studies of recent history, assist in American studies in other countries, fund creative writing and initiate major grants in music and other arts. Fahs attends the ACLS Conference on Scholarly Research in the Humanities and Social Sciences, Meeting of the Third Major Project Committee of the US National Commission for UNESCO and Conference on North African Problems. He also plans for his trip to the Middle East.
    Middle East; Libraries; Humanities; Education; Dance; City planning; United States; Diaries; Music
  - Trip to the Middle East - Index, 1960 January 9-April 7; Fahs, Charles B. (Charles Burton); Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Humanities. (Box 145, Reel M Fah 7, Frame 404)
    Athens, Beirut, Cairo.
    Index; Trip to Middle East (Athens, Beirut, Cairo); 3 pages.
    Lebanon; indexes (reference sources); Humanities; Greece; Egypt; Education
  - Trip to the Middle East, 1960 January 9-April 7; Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Humanities.; Fahs, Charles B. (Charles Burton); 121 pages (Reel M Fah 7, Frame 407, Box 145)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Fahs discusses projects and proposals with professionals in the field of humanities. He is involved in the progress of Humanities Division programs, selection of fellows and grant in-aid, and development of new research. The aims of the Humanities Division are to identify and stimulate new cultural growth, assist in interpretative studies of recent history, assist in American studies in other countries, fund creative writing and initiate major grants in music and other arts. Fahs travels to the Middle East, Chicago and Appleton-Neeah, Wisconsin. The New York City Center of Music and Drama, Inc.'s Kabuki Drama program is discussed as well.
    Diaries; East Asia; Education; Egypt; Greece; Humanities; Italy; Kabuki; Language and languages; Lebanon; Middle East; United States
  - Trip to Japan and Korea- Index, 1960 April 8-May 7; Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Humanities.; Fahs, Charles B. (Charles Burton) (Box 146, Reel M Fah 7, Frame 528)
    Index; Trip to Japan and Korea; 3 pages.
    Korea; Education; Humanities; indexes (reference sources); Japan
  - Trip to Japan and Korea, 1960 April 8-May 7; Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Humanities.; Fahs, Charles B. (Charles Burton); 76 pages (Box 146, Reel M Fah 7, Frame 534)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Fahs discusses projects and proposals with professionals in the field of humanities. He is involved in the progress of Humanities Division programs, selection of fellows and grant in-aid, and development of new research. The aims of the Humanities Division are to identify and stimulate new cultural growth, assist in interpretative studies of recent history, assist in American studies in other countries, fund creative writing and initiate major grants in music and other arts. Fahs travels to Japan and Korea. He tours their universities and libraries and assesses their humanities programs. The Stanford Seminar is discussed.
    Education; Drama; Japan; Humanities; Libraries; Korea; Philosophy and religion; Writing; Universities and colleges; Diaries
  - 1960 May 9-June 30, Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Humanities.; Fahs, Charles B. (Charles Burton); 113 pages (Reel M Fah 7, Frame 613, Box 146)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Fahs discusses projects and proposals with professionals in the field of humanities. He is involved in the progress of Humanities Division programs, selection of fellows and grant in-aid, and development of new research. The aims of the Humanities Division are to identify and stimulate new cultural growth, assist in interpretative studies of recent history, assist in American studies in other countries, fund creative writing and initiate major grants in music and other arts. Fahs tours Dartmouth College.
    Philosophy and religion; United States; Linguistics; Diaries; Music; Education; East Asia; Language and languages; Humanities
  - 1960 July 1-September 30, Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Humanities.; Fahs, Charles B. (Charles Burton); 124 pages (Reel M Fah 7, Frame 728, Box 146)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Fahs discusses projects and proposals with professionals in the field of humanities. He is involved in the progress of Humanities Division programs, selection of fellows and grant in-aid, and development of new research. The aims of the Humanities Division are to identify and stimulate new cultural growth, assist in interpretative studies of recent history, assist in American studies in other countries, fund creative writing and initiate major grants in music and other arts. Fahs takes a trip to Interlochen, Michigan, Seattle and Tanglewood, Massachusetts to survey National Music Camp, Sino-American Conference on Intellectual Cooperation and Berkshire Music Center, respectively.
    East Asia; Education; Dance; Diaries; Language and languages; Linguistics; Encyclopedias and dictionaries; Humanities; United States; Music; Religion
  - 1960 October 4-December 9, Fahs, Charles B. (Charles Burton); Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Humanities.; 94 pages (Reel M Fah 7, Frame 852, Box 146)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Fahs discusses projects and proposals with professionals in the field of humanities. He is involved in the progress of Humanities Division programs, selection of fellows and grant in-aid, and development of new research. The aims of the Humanities Division are to identify and stimulate new cultural growth, assist in interpretative studies of recent history, assist in American studies in other countries, fund creative writing and initiate major grants in music and other arts. Fahs attends Conference on Coordination and Evaluation of Graduate Foreign Language and Area Fellowship Programs (NDEA) and the Ballet Society Conference.
    Education; Drama; Dance; Linguistics; Language and languages; Humanities; History; United States; Diaries; Religion; Art
  - Trip to the Middle East, 1960 December 8-20; Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Humanities.; Fahs, Charles B. (Charles Burton); 25 pages (Box 146, Reel M Fah 7, Frame 946)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Fahs discusses projects and proposals with professionals in the field of humanities. He is involved in the progress of Humanities Division programs, selection of fellows and grant in-aid, and development of new research. The aims of the Humanities Division are to identify and stimulate new cultural growth, assist in interpretative studies of recent history, assist in American studies in other countries, fund creative writing and initiate major grants in music and other arts. Fahs takes a trip to the Middle East.
    Art; Diaries; Language and languages; Linguistics; Iraq; Libraries; History; Translations; Greece; Philosophy and religion
  - 1960 December 22-1961 April 7, Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Humanities.; Fahs, Charles B. (Charles Burton); 136 pages (Box 146, Reel M Fah 7, Frame 971)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Fahs discusses projects and proposals with professionals in the field of humanities. He is involved in the progress of Humanities Division programs, selection of fellows and grant in-aid, and development of new research. The aims of the Humanities Division are to identify and stimulate new cultural growth, assist in interpretative studies of recent history, assist in American studies in other countries, fund creative writing and initiate major grants in music and other arts. Fahs takes a trip to Guatemala, Mexico and Nigeria. He attends UNESCO Third Major Project Committee Meeting.
    Drama; Art; Dance; History; Humanities; Education; Guatemala; Mexico; Nigeria; Language and languages; Linguistics; Anthropology; United States; Diaries
  - Trip to Japan - Index, 1961 April 8-May 3; Fahs, Charles B. (Charles Burton); Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Humanities. (Box 146, Reel M Fah 7, Frame 1,110)
    Index; Trip to Japan; 5 pages.
    Humanities; Japan; Diaries; Education
  - Trip to Japan, 1961 April 8-May 3; Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Humanities.; Fahs, Charles B. (Charles Burton); 82 pages (Reel M Fah 7, Frame 1,115, Box 146)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Fahs discusses projects and proposals with professionals in the field of humanities. He is involved in the progress of Humanities Division programs, selection of fellows and grant in-aid, and development of new research. The aims of the Humanities Division are to identify and stimulate new cultural growth, assist in interpretative studies of recent history, assist in American studies in other countries, fund creative writing and initiate major grants in music and other arts. Fahs takes a trip to Japan.
    Libraries; Linguistics; Music; Religion; Education; Humanities; Japan; Language and languages; Art; Diaries; United States; Translations
  - 1961 May 4-June 30, Fahs, Charles B. (Charles Burton); Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Humanities.; 72 pages (Reel M Fah 7, Frame 1,197, Box 146)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Fahs discusses projects and proposals with professionals in the field of humanities. He is involved in the progress of Humanities Division programs, selection of fellows and grant in-aid, and development of new research. The aims of the Humanities Division are to identify and stimulate new cultural growth, assist in interpretative studies of recent history, assist in American studies in other countries, fund creative writing and initiate major grants in music and other arts. Fahs attends meeting of Committee on Asia and visits Columbia University to survey the Program of Electronic Music.
    United States; Music; Humanities; History; Education; Diaries
  - 1961 July 5-September 28, Fahs, Charles B. (Charles Burton); Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Humanities.; 68 pages (Box 146, Reel M Fah 7, Frame 1,271)
    United States; Music; Humanities; History; Education; Poetry; Diaries; Art
- Fairchild, Alexander G. B.
  - 1935-1937 (Box 147)
- Fendall, Neville Rex Edwards (N. R. E.)
  - 1964-1965 (Box 147)
- Ferrell, John A.
  Biographical/Historical note
  Born in North Carolina, John Atkinson Ferrell (1880-1965) received both his B.S. (1902) and M.D. (1907) from The University of North Carolina. Ferrell next matriculated to Johns Hopkins where he earned a Ph.D. in 1919. Feller later received an LL.D degree from the University of North Carolina, the North Carolina Distinguished Service Award and the recognition of an Honorary Fellow from the Royal Institute of Public Health.
  Ferrell began his career as a teacher in Sampson County, North Carolina. Rising through the categories, Ferrell transitioned from a medical practitioner and County Superintendent, to the Superintendent of Health for Duplin Country, N.C. and later, the Assistant Secretary for the State Board of Health. In 1944, John Atkinson Ferrell became the Medical Director for the John and Mary Markle Foundation before ultimately assuming the role of the Executive Secretary for the North Carolina Medical Care Commission. In and among his professional career, Ferrell was an active member of numerous associations and organizations. From 1910 to 1913, John Ferrell acted as the State Director for the Rockefeller Sanitary Commission for the Eradication of Hookworm Disease. Subsequently, he assumed the role of Associate Director of the International Health Division of the Rockefeller Foundation for a lengthy thirty-one years, ranging from 1913-1944. During this time, Ferrell published Hookworm Disease; Its Ravages, Prevention and Cure in a Rockefeller Foundation Publication. It is also important to note that Ferrell published his writing on Wickliffe Rose, who acted as the Executive Secretary of the Rockefeller Sanitary Commission for the Eradication of Hookworm Disease from 1910-1915 and the General Director of the International Health Board for the Rockefeller foundation from 1913-1923.
  Apart from his work with the Rockefellers, Ferrell served as Chairman for the National Malaria Committee, the American Public Health Association and the American Medical Association. Moreover, Ferrell was a member of the Royal Institute of Public Health in Great Britain, the Medical Society of North Carolina (Secretary, 1912-1915), the Medical Society of Union County N.J., the Cosmos Club of Washington D.C., the Town Hall Club of New York and the Delta Omega professional honor society.
  - Journal - Central American Journey, 1915 November 11-December 13; Rockefeller Foundation; Ferrell, John A. (John Atkinson); 35 pages (Reel M Fer 1, Frame 1, Box 148)
    This diary is both a travelogue and report of Dr. Ferrell's 1915 trip to British Honduras (Belize), Guatemala, and Salvador (El Salvador) on behalf of the International Health Board, providing his observations of the state of public health, economic life, and culture in the three Central American nations. In the diary, Dr. Ferrell inspects the clinical and public health facilities available to the native populations and reports that the government officials in each nation are eager for support from the IHB in establishing public health campaigns to eradicate Hookworm Disease, Tuberculosis, and Malaria. He also provides his endorsement for several native medical professionals who he believes would be indispensable to the IHB's work in establishing native medical institutions and who would be deserving of IHB scholarships. Where statistical information is available, Dr. Ferrell collects figures on rates of infection and morbidity resulting from Hookworm disease, mostly from plantations in Guatemala and Salvador where the data is collected by corporate owners, the largest being the United Fruit Company, whose facilities in Guatemala are extensively reported on. Dr. Ferrell also reports on his time in Guatemala and Salvador as the guest and colleague of Dr. Walter H. Rowan, Director of the Guatemalan branch of the International Health Board, who helps him to secure an agreement with the Consejo Superior de Salubridad (National Department of Health) for the immediate establishment of an IHB public health campaign in the Republic of Salvador.
    Tuberculosis; Public health; Sanitation; Hookworm disease; Malaria; Central America; Diaries
  - Notes Concerning Trip to Mexico, 1927 April 21-May 2; Rockefeller Foundation; Ferrell, John A. (John Atkinson); 13 pages (Box 148, Reel M Fer 1, Frame 36)
    Scope and Contents
    This diary provides Dr. Ferrell's observations on the state of public health affairs in Mexico on the federal, state, and local level. Visiting Mexico City, Jalapa, and Tierra Blanca, he is given a tour by Dr. Henry P. Carr, who is in charge of the RF's Mexican operations, and Dr. Jose Zozaya, Director of the Institute of Hygiene, of the recently built federal, state, and local public health facilities. Ferrell's summary of the tour suggests that these facilities are extravagantly built, taxing on Mexico's strained economy and government budgets, and highlight the lack of cooperation between federal, state, and local authorities. This concern is expressed in Dr. Ferrell's final recommendations, where he also praises the work of Dr. Carr, which has led to a "sanitary triumph" in Mexico, and suggests shifting operational focus from Hookworm Disease to Malaria containment.
    Diaries; Sanitation; Mexico; Public health; Hookworm disease; Malaria
  - Exhibit A, 26 April 1927; Rockefeller Foundation; Ferrell, John A. (John Atkinson)
    Exhibit "A" Address by John A. Ferrell at dinner with the Mexican Federal Department of Health.
  - Exhibit B, Ferrell, John A. (John Atkinson); Rockefeller Foundation
    An interview given by Ferrell regarding his observations on Vera Cruz.
- Fischelis, Robert L.
  - 1966 (Box 149)
  - 1967 January-July (Box 149)
  - 1967 August-December (Box 149)
  - 1968 January-April 1 (Box 150)
  - 1968 April 2-June 3 (Box 150)
  - 1968 June 6-July 18 (Box 150)
  - 1968 July 19-December 20 (Box 150)
  - 1969 January 7-March 31 (Box 150)
  - 1969 March 31-May 21 (Box 150)
  - 1969 May 22-August 14 (Box 150)
  - 1969 September 17-December 19 (Box 150)
  - 1970 January-March 16 (Box 151)
  - 1970 March 18-May 18 (Box 151)
  - 1970 May 19-August 18 (Box 151)
  - 1970 August 18-December 14 (Box 151)
  - 1971 January-April 14 (Box 151)
  - 1971 April 14-August 3 (Box 151)
  - 1971 August 3-September 23 (Box 151)
  - 1971 September 23-December 26 (Box 151)
  - 1972 January 7-May 9 (Box 152)
  - 1972 May 9-August 9 (Box 152)
  - 1972 August 9-December 30 (Box 152)
  - 1973 January 3-May 25 (Box 152)
  - 1973 May 29-September 6 (Box 152)
  - 1973 September 6-December 28 (Box 152)
  - 1974 January 2-May 3 (Box 153)
  - 1974 May 3-August 7 (Box 153)
  - 1974 August 11-December (Box 153)
  - 1975 (Box 153)
  - 1976 January-July (Box 153)
  - 1976 August-December (Box 153)
  - 1977 January-July (Box 154)
  - 1977 August-1978 January 2 (Box 154)
- Flahiff, Edward W.
  - 1938-1941 (Box 154)
- Fosdick, Raymond B.
  Raymond B. Fosdick was a man with philanthropic interests and great administrative talents who played an instrumental role in directing the Rockefeller Foundation (RF).
  Fosdick was born in Buffalo, New York, in 1883. He pursued his post-secondary education at Princeton University, receiving his B.A. in 1905 and his M.A. in 1906. His decision to study at Princeton helped to set the trajectory of his career. While there, he met and befriended Woodrow Wilson, who was then president of the University. Wilson's internationalist philosophy and interest in social problems had a profound effect in shaping Fosdick's worldview and, later, his term of leadership at the RF.
  While still a student, Fosdick visited New York City's Lower East Side. The living conditions of many of the city's immigrant families appalled him, and after graduating from Princeton, he took a position at the Henry Street Settlement, which provided social services to poor families in that neighborhood. Fosdick continued to work there while also pursuing a law degree, which he received from New York Law School in 1908.
  Upon completing law school, Fosdick took a position as investigator for the City of New York. It was here, while investigating white slavery, that he met John D. Rockefeller, Jr. (JDR Jr.), who was at that time working with a special grand jury tasked with investigating the same issue.
  In 1913 Fosdick was hired by JDR Jr. to head up a study for the newly created Bureau of Social Hygiene (BSH). The Bureau was created following JDR Jr.'s work as a member of the grand jury, and it was tasked with the study and prevention of a number of social ills related to urban poverty, including prostitution, venereal disease, and crime. He was hired to conduct a study focusing on European law enforcement, which was published as European Police Systems in 1916, but a follow-up study on American police systems was halted because of World War I.
  In 1917 Fosdick took leave from the BSH when he was commissioned by the Secretary of War to study military training for the United States Army and Navy. Fosdick then went on to serve as a special representative of the War Department in France and as a civilian aide to General John J. Pershing. At war's end Fosdick formally resigned from the BSH upon being named Under-Secretary General to the League of Nations. While he firmly believed in the mandate of the League, he ultimately left the position in 1920 when the United States failed to ratify its membership in the organization.
  In 1920 Fosdick returned to the BSH and finally completed his long-delayed study on American police systems. He continued his close association with JDR Jr., serving as both his attorney and advisor. This relationship ultimately led to Fosdick's prominent role in the Rockefeller family's philanthropies.
  In 1921 Fosdick became a board member at the RF, the Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research (RIMR), the Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial (LSRM), the China Medical Board (CMB) and the International Health Division (IHD). One year later he was appointed a member of the General Education Board (GEB), and in 1923 he became a member of the International Education Board (IEB). As a trustee of the RF, Fosdick played a key role in the Foundation's reorganization in 1928, and in 1936 he was named president of both the RF and GEB.
  As president of the RF, Fosdick, along with JDR Jr., shaped the direction of the organization between 1936 and 1948. In these years the organization contributed substantially to the research and control of malaria and yellow fever, as well as to the modernization of China and the development of the natural sciences. During this time the RF also developed its first programs in the humanities and social sciences, as well as a revolutionary program in agriculture in the hopes of expanding crop production worldwide.
  Fosdick's work in public service and philanthropy resulted in many awards during his lifetime. These included the Distinguished Service Medal for his war work, and the titles of Commander in the French Legion of Honor and Fellow of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences. He was also a prolific writer, authoring fourteen books, including The Story of the Rockefeller Foundation.
  Raymond B. Fosdick died at his home in Newtown, Connecticut, in 1972. He was 89 years old.